everyone this is active inference guest
stream
70.1 it's February 9th
2024 we're here with Jerry macowski and
this should be a great presentation
discussion conversation knowledge
experience so Jerry thank you very much
for joining and please let us begin
however you prefer
thank you so much it's a delight to be
here with you and uh I feel like what
you were reading a moment ago was like a
star date into it a star date entry and
like we're cruising off to some
interesting New Horizon and what I want
to do is um build some conversational
background here by showing what I've
been doing for 26 years with a a quirky
mind mapping tool called the brain and
then how that cuts into or crosses into
or blossoms into topics of interest to
both of us us uh and and hopefully to
people who are
watching um but at first I think I I
want to say set a little background just
for for what this is uh I used to be a
tech industry Trends analyst I spent uh
11 and a half years with a little
company called new science
associates uh which I have in my brain
over here and I'm just going to use the
brain for a moment to show you what what
it is uh I was with new with new science
uh back in the day and I started two of
their seven Research Services so in 1990
I started a research service called
intelligent document
management uh and then a couple years
later I started a uh research service
called continuous information
environments and if you were to look at
the intelligent document management
scope diagram which I drew back then in
1990 we used to refer to this as the
bubble chart and um at that time our
major competitor was Gartner group there
were a couple other endless houses like
bisap and I BS IDC and a few others but
all everybody's pitch documents to
clients were bullet points here's the
list of the Technologies we cover and I
drew this diagram uh the founders of new
science had asked me to create a service
based on electronic Imaging and I went
to and looked at electronic Imaging I
was like wow this is really a dumb
technology we're going to scan checks
and things like that and we're going to
put them on optical storage and then try
to bring them up and reprint them onto
somebody's printed uh AMX invoice kind
of thing that was the most famous
Imaging thing at the time so I looked
around databases and moving objects
around networks and I assembled uh a
service that I called intelligent
document management and this service cut
across um a bunch of categories that
Gartner didn't know how to cut across
because if you were a Gartner client you
either had to call the mid-range or the
or the PC or the M Mainframe service or
the word processing service or work
Workforce autom workplace automation
service and this So within a year or two
Gartner and everybody needed to have a
conceptual map of their service and also
a lot of others needed to start
reconfiguring their offers because our
offer happened to be pitched to the
problems clients had as opposed to the
structure of the
industry uh and then I will also add
that if you look here and squint a
little bit you'll see the beginnings of
the worldwide web uh which I had no
knowledge of I had no inkling that there
was any research going on about the
worldwide web but I have document recog
nition and sgml and a couple other
things in here uh which later become
really important components because the
worldwide web is HTML which is a skinny
down version of sgml and we've got
document architectures complex documents
things like that and then uh if you
squint and look at the continuous
information environments research
Service uh you will sort of see
smartphones on the horizon and and I'm
doing this I'm not really good at
self-promotion but I'm doing this to say
that um I'm pretty reasonably good at
sniffing at what's coming I usually
don't name it the right thing but I'm
poking in the right directions and I've
I've kind of done this a bunch of times
in my career and I I have sort of trust
that that that these things just show up
over time and uh and one of the things
that helps me keep track of this and
understand it is this weird little brain
software that I've been showing you here
so new science associates uh this is a
link to uh actually I don't think
there's a yes I think I think I bought
the domain new science associates.com
because it was avail able because the
company is so old and got eaten by
Gartner later that it had no website and
I was like you know we should have a
website uh but they were part of Gartner
Group which is uh technology actually
under industy analysts and here are a
whole bunch of different industry
analyst firms the brain is organized so
that uh there are each node is is called
a thought you can only connect thoughts
to each other through these three
circles that every thought has up down
and left and there's no circle to the
right for reasons that only become
apparent once you start using this thing
which means as you're feeding stuff into
the brain you have to decide is this
above or below or beside other things
the brain doesn't tell you um what where
anything should go and it doesn't sort
of care meaning there's no consistency
logic checking in the brain there's no
AI in the brain uh it doesn't need or
want a taxonomy you could design an
ontology or taxonomy in here but it's
not doing any uh structured checking on
what you're doing it it's just like
Photoshop for nodes for ideas nodes and
links right but this one constraint of
going up down or left was actually
incredibly interesting and important and
it was really good for me because back
in that day I was a tech industry Trends
analyst and I needed to know who
competes with whom and I will go to um
I'll just give a really
practical I'll just give a really
practical uh example of what I mean I'll
go to the venture capital Capal firm
andrees and Horowitz which I have under
VC firms and uh these are sort of the
major VC firms but one day I realized oh
there's a whole mess of other VC firms
uh this is the list of other VCS and
you'll see that there's a scroll bar
down here this is just a through C of
venture capital
firms and the way I aggregated these was
not by exhaustively uh uploading or
going through some database and and and
sucking that in this was just the ones
that appeared over time backing
different companies I was looking at and
then articles that would mention one or
whatever else uh all of those kinds of
things happening slowly over time so
here's Chase Capital which invested in
geoc cities Scout electromedia and
square trade uh what was what business
was square trade in oh they were they
were doing Trust Services I don't think
I have a lot in Trust Services so
project tandis and square trade uh which
is under reputation and trust these W's
you might recognize as Wikipedia uh fave
icons and so I use
in fact anywhere you see a fave icon
attached to a thought and you see a lot
of Wikipedia ones but here for example
is a a fave icon for uh the world
economic Forum because this website uh
the URL that I've attached to this
thought will take us over to the world
economic Forum
website uh so I've been curating this
thing by hand for 26 years I was on
their first press tour uh December of 97
in fact I was recently digging through
some boxes of old files of mine and
found the packet they mailed me with you
know paper documentation about the
product which i' only ever just heard of
then and a cup letter that said we're
really looking forward to meeting you uh
in your offices and I remember when the
inventor opened his laptop and showed me
the first version of this which didn't
look that much different from this I
will say that over 26 years this thing
has looked consistently this similar um
I helped prevent it from changing
dramatically some were 10 years ago
where the inventor was going to do
something radically different and I was
like you know you're going to lose all
the secret magic of of this thing uh
that you've got this brain
software and um as I said I was busy
covering uh covering technology
companies and I needed to know who
competes with whom who invests with whom
so here's uh andrees and Horowitz uh
basically invested in canvas which was
an image board um oh I know I've got a
whole bunch more stuff on image boards
uh but here's for CH for example uh
which is an online community that allows
for anonymous posting here are other
services that allow for anonymous
posting uh I've got them under minimal
censorship spaces online but opposite
cyber bullying which is a major issue
and I'm just giving a random tour
through kind of what's up and what
what's catches what catches my eye but
because I'm the person who's put all
these thoughts in and I've never done it
automatically I've never crawled the
website and had all the the links or the
pages in the website put into the brand
which was an early feature that it did
have I could have called my my uh file
system my Explorer or my finder I could
have had all every file represented here
in some kind of free structure I never
wanted to do that because I knew that
the name space inside the brain was
really important and I wanted to be able
to find things and now um all I need to
do to jump someplace is I I click
somewhere in the blue background by the
way this blue gradient background is the
background that the brain shipped with
27 26 years ago and I've never changed
it because the VIS the readability is
really good I have no reason to make it
an image you could if you wanted to it
just makes it harder to read so I'm very
old school in the brain there are also a
lot of really Nifty features like I
could add uh uh thought types and Link
types and I could add tags and labels I
don't use any of those things uh not
because I hate metadata but because I
believe that anything that makes me that
makes it take longer for me to add
things into to curate my brain is
actually going to slow me down and maybe
make me stop using this tool I would
love for something to go through and say
oh this looks like an author and this
looks like a book they wrote I'm happy
to tag this up as a book this person up
as an author the link up as written by
and wrote this and you know off we go to
the races with metadata because I think
metadata is super important but this is
the file I'm I'm I'm sharing with you is
the file that I added stuff to this
morning is the file that I started 2 six
years ago so I I'm also unusual among
brain users in that I have one one big
brain that I've curated for all that
period of time uh which is a little
weird but I think really pretty
interesting because I have this very
deep felt experience of um the
aggregation of information in a space
that maps to how I think and what I
think and and what I care about right so
um for example I have a thought called
big questions oh I was just going to
explain how I jump to to a thought so if
I if I click anywhere in that blue
background that's how I got distracted
it puts my cursor in the search bar I
then type any unique string and because
i' I've added all the all these uh nodes
I kind of know what the words are and
sometimes I put uh words that that I
know are unique because I can find
things very quickly that way so I knew I
had thing called Big questions and so
here's uh one big question is rethinking
and renot ating the social contract uh
because I think that we are
involuntarily re renegotiating the
social contract around the world there's
a whole bunch of protest movements that
I'll point to here the ghon extinction
Rebellion Occupy Wall Street and Occupy
Wall Street has a bunch of stuff under
it so here's articles about occupy back
in the day I created this thought back
in
right and so I'm having this unusual
experience that most people don't get to
have of seeing revisiting improving and
updating all the things that seemed
important back when ever since 1997 J
let's call it January
1998 and I think I've learned a lot how
to take notes and how to add things to
my brain since then so I think my
curating gets better over
time but um I don't delete a lot of
things in my brain because I think as
Nasim taleb
uh uh
we never hear from the graveyard
basically in the Black Swan Nim TB says
uh you know it's good to know all the
companies that tried and failed to do
something if I go to Buddy lists in my
brain here's buddy list boom see how
quick it is to get there I I can't do
this in any database program I can't do
this in any other kind of app so this is
a list of the buddy list that I saw go
by uh so moralist did icq uh I added
them in December of 97 so this is one of
the first thoughts I ever added to my
brain this is this is when I started
using the brain so moris is one of the
first companies I put in they're under
Israeli
startups here's a bunch of those if I go
back to moris uh Yosi vard's son aric is
one of the three founders but I met Yosi
because he wrote he sent me an email
after I wrote about them in the
newsletter I used to write for Esther
Dyson and so I got to know Yosi and give
him a little attention about all this um
but not knowing all these companies
tried and died to do this doesn't help
us we then keep repeating the same
errors uh thanks to the internet archive
which I don't think goes back to 1997
but thanks to the internet archive you
can see a lot of these URLs and what
they had way back when which is terrific
in fact there's a couple URLs that I've
tracked for long enough where if you go
to the archive you'll see three little
bell curves which is originally when
launched this thing was this company and
it got some attention and then it died
and maybe the URL got acquired or the
company revamped itself and repitched
itself and came out again and here is
its second Lifetime and then here you
can see their third lifetime which may
go to the present day which I find
fascinating because it's it's as if
there's an archaeological layers here
like this is you know like a tell where
as you dig down you can start to uncover
different archaeological layers of what
happened uh each thought in my brain as
I've just been showing you has time
stamps in it uh but until recently there
wasn't really an API so this was not
programmatically accessible
and so I've I've never done any kind of
analysis to say if you were to shave
back to this layer what would you see or
to do a visual reconstruction of what I
added I also don't care what this looks
like from a 30,000 foot level it would
be a big ball of twine and and there's a
lot of visualizations out there that
look like big balls of twine I don't
find them especially
interesting um let me bounce up uh to a
different place just to talk about to
put the brain in context
um
oops I that didn't work very well let's
try this
again there mapping tools for thinking
is a place where
um uh late last year the year before I
had a project with beta Works uh they
had a camp around tools for thinking
which is a nice name for the category of
tools like the brain like Rome research
obsidian uh kumu uh there's all the
different mapping tools outliner tools
uh all those kinds of things and I
realized that I had all those
subcategories but they were just
subcategories they weren't connected
together so I created this thought uh in
April of 22 and then I went around
looking for all the different places
where I had you know personal knowledge
graphs
pkgs well somebody else did distributed
knowledge graphs or dkg there's also
Enterprise knowledge graphs uh there's
just knowledge graphs in general which
all of those should be under right and
then U Gordon brander is creating the
noosphere protocol as part of his
startup called subconscious over here
but if I go back to mapping tools for
thinking these all uh are you know
collaborative decision-making tools
really interesting and now we're seeing
uh machine learning for
decisionmaking and I'll also add that
when I first joined new science
associates I was their neural networks
analyst and so I've been watching as gen
basically got birthed um now the
earliest neural network researchers back
in the 40s and 50s when people first had
computers one of the first things they
tried to do is figure out how to make
these computers emulate human thinking
and the ones who decided to follow the
neurobiology uh created neural networks
the ones who decided to follow the logic
created expert systems there's a whole
train of thinking there that I can map
in my in my brain here but I you'll see
that now I now have ml4 ml4 ml4 uh ml4
hacking and cyber crime there's only one
article here written by Bruce schneer
who is an awesome writer called academic
the coming AI hackers in
2021 and then here is an article that
cites that book written by Nathan
Sanders in the New York Times because
here you see a New York Times uh URL and
here you'll see sentences that I cut and
pasted out of that article because this
is how I note take
now um so here's again back to mapping
tools we thinking a cool thing is that I
can actually uh send somebody a URL that
will take them to a specific thought in
my
brain another thing I'll I'll say about
this brain thing is that um the brains
inventors and a few other power users
have been trying to figure out how to
lose this complicated interface for a
really long time this is sort of
daunting to a lot of people um I have no
concept that um everybody should be
using something like the brain but I do
think more of us should be sharing what
we think and what we know in some open
way
and I'm really one of my major projects
right now is to figure out how to do
that what to do it and
um and just because
uh retype that with
spaces uh and because that is difficult
to
explain um if you ask me what Wikipedia
is I can tell you it is an encyclopedia
written with a Wiki uh funded by VA
donations that lives on the web and is a
completely open source project you can
run this software yourself you can use
the content yourself you can participate
in all their conversations I can tell
you what Wikipedia is and Wikipedia is
pretty popular be partly because it's
that simple and it does in fact rely on
volunteers to come in and change you
know change edit uh update uh its
entries the space I'm looking at is
philosophically above that and not just
reference pages in encyclopedia but
opinions belief systems what does qanon
believe what does Maga believe believe
what do what do progressives believe
what's the difference between different
kinds of anarchism so
um so if I go to anarchism for example
here's on anarchism which is a Chomsky
book here's the topic of anarchism I
have types of anarchism there were lots
of different types of anarchism and they
all have Wikipedia Pages nicely enough
um and so anarcho pacifism I don't know
that much about but I know that thorough
and Tolstoy were anaco pacifists and I
don't remember putting Bart in there uh
but I did that in 2012 and I didn't
connect him to any of his works or
anything else so I don't know really who
he is I'd have to go back and look him
up again but the idea of being able to
go around and do this now how do I meld
what I think and what I believe with
what you believe Daniel how does that
work right and so I bought the domain
the big fungus. org in 2021 because I
needed a tongue and cheek metaphorically
really rich way of explaining that I
hope before I die that the data in my
brain is an inoculation into the big
fungus that lives between us where we
make mycelial connections to each other
exchange nutrients in fertile soil and
that the fruiting bodies of our efforts
the mushrooms that pop out of mycelial
networks actually become the edible
tradable sharable artifacts so I have a
project that meets on Mondays these days
called Neo books where we're trying to
reinvent books books where the the
notion of using a book is just in fact
I'll go to neob
books um the notion of the Neo
book here are the calls here is the
project um a Neo book is basically the
fruiting body of the big
fungus the the book version of uh the
artifact is just something that people
would recognize oh this looks like a
book smells like a book I understand
this but the interesting parts of the
the book the Neo book is composed of
nuggets that roll up into chapters that
roll up into a book you put some front
matter and end matter around it you
squeeze it out as an Epub or as a Kindle
file format book and you have a book you
can print on demand that that looks like
a book but the book is just bait to get
people to come play with the Nuggets
that are live documents on the web that
are Wiki style Plus+ basically anybody
who's had a good time in a Wiki Online
and I've just described a very tiny set
of humans on the planet knows that
collaboratively editing a collection of
pages that matter is a joyful task that
leads to really useful uh fruits you
know useful products and most people
only ever experienced that through
Wikipedia which works right Wikipedia
works pretty well despite having been
through a lot of dark times and
difficult issues um if I were a
14-year-old boy I would like nothing
more than to go in and spam Wikipedia
and try to hurt it um and Wikipedia will
gently take that and try to convert you
into an editor and a contributor because
they know that the best thing they might
be able to do is
that so one of my projects is this idea
of the big fungus and then I I I host
four standing calls every week uh all of
which I record on YouTube and then Post
online so the neob books calls are more
more recent than the rest of them uh but
this is a batch of calls that uh that
you can go watch on you know online if
you were to find this thought and you
were to go to the uh the the call we had
November 6th of 2023 here are the things
we referenced and then here's some here
are some notes I take I took uh during
that call uh so we talked about neob
books in of course it was a neob book
call so we do that often but we talked
about web bugs I don't remember talking
about web bugs but they were beacons or
pixels that were of kind of a
surveillance technology that would tell
you when I had looked at a web page for
example right so now you can go back and
see all the different calls that I've
been part
of um let me just go to
ogm zoom calls here's here's like the
big bucket of calls I've posted for the
last three years since the p pandemic
started and there's a scroll bar down
here the main calls are on Thursday
mornings ogm is open Global mind which
is a community of practice I started uh
as as uh lockdown took us all into zoom
and these calls are still going and
we're busy chewing on uh the ideas of
uh the name open Global mind is always
what I had in the back of my head as
what would an open- Source col collab
highly collaborative version of the
brain look like that didn't require
everybody to come in using the brain it
would let you do an outliner or
something else and we could kind of talk
in between and so I always thought of it
and I bought the domain uh quite a while
ago and then as we started having these
conversations I'm like oh let's call Our
Community open Global mind
because the community is about both
being open minded and about building a
Global
mind and these things kind of go hand in
hand because I can show you what I know
and what I care about and if you don't
trust me and if we don't have some kind
of connection or if you're not
open-minded in some way you're never
going to listen to me and we're just
going to disagree forever and my hope is
that by making more explicit our belief
systems and putting them in the world
and and by the way gen ai's emergence
has made this both more complicated and
more exciting I'm happy to talk about
that um but by doing by putting our
ideas in the world we might actually
reduce conflict and instead of being in
Mexican standoffs all around the world
by the way um we could actually start to
productively solve some of the problems
that we're facing together because I do
think that we're facing five crises six
crises a poly crisis a meta crisis I you
there's it's certainly got lots of
different names right uh but and I and
I so if I type in five crises I can go
to we are in the midddle of f five
crises the poly crisis and for me some
of them are was 2006 Peak democracy at
the time the covid pandemic black lives
matter the effects of climate change uh
inflation as Russia invades Ukraine was
a temporary one uh which seems to be
going down but this is kind of a place
where I I also have a Nexus a collection
of what some of these crises are and
what we're what we're doing about it um
and then
and then connected to that I have
communities trying to fix world problems
and here's uh the knowledge Society the
global Solutions initiative and spiral
Network out in New Zealand uh Society
2045 stronger together X Humanity 2050
uh the gry swan Guild uh Doomer
optimism um Black Sheep game B Community
melium common Future these are all
communities uh that are trying to do so
if I go to game B uh here's articles
about game B here's Jim rot who I put in
my brain in 2006 for example J's been
here forever connected to Santa Fe
Institute uses Rome has a family
Foundation uh etc
etc so this is just an intro
to the tool that changed my life 26
years ago how I use it how I'm thinking
in it I this is a solitary task I I I
like say that I feel like a lone ant at
the fungus face which requires a little
explaining because leaf cutter ants uh
and you've talked about stigmergic
Communications here before which I love
um if I can spell stigmergy properly
nope it's IG g m e there we go um so
leaf cutter ants can't actually digest
leaves why are they bringing all these
leaves into their hive well they hand
them off to a subclass of that kind of
ant which mulches them up and feeds them
to a fungus basically inoculates the
fungus which metabolizes the leaf matter
and oozes little drops of nectar and
little bits little globules called
something or other it's in my brain um
which Feed The Hive so symbiotic
relationship happy fungus happy Hive and
the days and there kind of hasn't been a
day in the last 26 years unless I was
traing across the step in Mongolia and
had no you know no computer with me
there hasn't been a day that I haven't
been an ant at this fungus face here
right which is why the big fungus showed
up for me as such a nice funny term
metaphorically for shared memory how do
we tell each other what we know and then
duke it out in a spirit of fair play to
figure out how we make better decisions
together over time that's really the the
core of what I care about now um and
Trust matters a lot in that as I said if
I don't trust you we can't Duke anything
out there will be no sense of fair play
there are a bunch of people in the arena
right now who are trying to undermine
fair play and make sure we destroy fair
play and people's uh you know faith in
the web in journalism in science in
politics and elections and all that and
I think that those things are not good
for humans in the long run and I'd like
to find a way to fix
those and um so active inference and the
free energy principle are in here as
well and I'm trying to figure out how to
understand them better uh so that I can
see whether and how these things all fit
and my undergrad was in economics really
econometrics and econometric is a whole
bunch of Matrix math which is about
minimizing lease squares errors that's
what it's about and guess what that
sounds like that sounds like the the
math that's inside of neural networks
and that sounds like the math that's
behind uh active inference and so there
there's something really interesting
there going on that I would love to
explore with you and anyone else so let
me let me hit pause there and uh see
where that all takes
us thank you Jerry awesome works so one
just specific followup before all some
more general questions and read some
live chat you mentioned up left down can
you just describe what those
specifically mean why does it matter and
what is the spatial metaphor and what
does that all do awesome thank you so
they can mean anything you want them to
the brain shows up and it doesn't tell
you how to use up left down it's just
that those are the only ways you can
create something so I'm going to go left
here and make a spirous link to neural
networks uh which I know I have of
course and I've just created a new link
going with this this uh lateral link
called a jump link and I'm going to
break it by doing two finger click and
saying
unlink the way I generally use this is
that this the super
category or the the collective noun or
whatever else goes up the the specifics
go down the detail goes down and then
the jump thought is for other things
that are really similar like neighbors
or really opposite like East
West right uh so I I will have often a a
thought which has opposite it critiques
of the name of that thought because hey
here's a bunch of evidence in favor of
that thought but you know what there's a
bunch of people that have some wise
critiques so for
example I'll go to
capitalism and then on the left I've got
a thought called critiques of capitalism
but then under I've got articles about
capitalism which is a I I've developed a
couple little tropes or I call them
cliches uh that I do consistently and if
you do things consistently in the brain
then it's much easier to navigate you
can really kind of get around and one of
my one of the things I do is when things
get crowded down below a thought I
create a thought called articles about
and then I put all the Artic all the
books you YouTube videos here's an
Harvard Business School article here's a
book on Amazon uh here's something from
the New York Review of Books uh here's
something from Salon magazine you can
tell just by the fave icons right and
and note that a lot of these um I I
usually put authors in so here's William
bomal The Economist who studied
entrepreneurship he also wrote the cost
disase etc etc so I always for example
put authors above their books I always
put actors under their movies because
they're acting in a movie and if a movie
is based on a novel The Novel will be
above the movie right or if a musical
got turned into film the music will be
above you know
Carousel I'm not sure Carousel is a
movie it must have been a movie somebody
made a movie no I guess not uh so here's
the the Rogers and Hammerstein musical
Carousel and you'll notice this isn't
just about tech companies and Tech
issues that we're subtly in musicals and
uh I've got musicals under types of
theater uh music in general uh and I
have like uh types of music over here
which should be pretty capacious
so Narco coridos I grew up in South
America so Narco coridos are a
subcategory of noro music that is about
Mexican drug cartels and here are some
of the Narco Coro Chalino Sanchez
apparently El Gand is another one these
are the the most famous Narco coros
writers so one of the things I love
about the brain is that there's always a
sense of
up because of this one little thing that
that Haron the inventor invented back
when there's always a sense of north or
up or something like that it's like when
when you're scuba diving the way to get
out of out of trouble is follow the
bubbles I've always got bubbles here and
they mean whatever I made them mean when
I started building this space I've met a
couple people who only do lateral links
and their brain was senseless to me I
couldn't follow it but early on they had
decided that this should look like an
outline going left right and you could
do that but it makes a mess it doesn't
turn out right and so um and also by the
way if the if the link is solid it means
there's something off to the the left
off off that gate if it's empty it means
there's nothing off that gate so here's
Mexican drug cartels so I have the
Mexican drug war opposite that not sure
that was a good use of opposite but
that's under the War on Drugs in general
uh which is under why does the US
imprison so many people and there's a
bunch of stuff there actually I like
this I've got it under stupid Wars we're
fighting so that was a little bit too
much explanation of up down left but but
I I think just by some examples you can
see how I'm using it and again anybody
who comes in and decides to start using
the brain atth brain.com uh and just
download and install the personal brain
try out the free version if you want to
do something like this uh can make up
how they want to how they want to do
these things and I think I was lucky in
that the moment harand opened his his
laptop and demoed it for me my wet brain
was like oh oh this is how I think and
then as I started using it I was
realizing oh I need to groove a couple
habits here and if I groove some habits
and if I'm careful about the name space
this will be useful later on um there's
a thought called uh
lessons lessons from 26 years of using
my brain which I I don't need to talk
about unless you're interested but this
is where I actually catalog insights
I've had about using this particular
tool to curate a memory for 26
years wow
awesome all right some questions from
live chat or is there any you want to
bring up or ask right now or I'll go to
a live chat question um go to live chat
and let's see where that takes us okay
let's start from the social end do you
have any thoughts on Doug Ang Gart
anything you'd want to add or let's look
it up and go from there sure so here's
Doug I got to meet Doug a couple times
while he was still alive once when he
was still pretty Lucid uh and once when
he was suffering from Alzheimer's toward
the end of his life uh Doug is one of
those people who gifted us these
brilliant ideas that are visible in the
mother of all demos uh which is the
famous 1968 demo that he did
uh where did I put
it I can't see where I put it up up
around so here's oh angelart 68 demo so
I've got it right here I I was looking
for these are all alphabetic down here
that's how I have ch child thoughts
organized but here's the mother of all
demos which gives us a whole bunch of
things uh like the Mouse and all those
kinds of things and he also then for the
rest of his career had trouble getting
funding didn't get more ideas out and
was a very difficult person to actually
sponsor and help uh keep inventing so
like Ted Nelson I would sort of bundle
them together um a bunch of really
interesting ideas and then thorny thorny
thorny uh like to try to develop their
ideas later on and they held on
to too many of their early early ideas
as if that were the only way to do
things both of them so that that's some
perspective I I just attended uh just a
a couple weeks ago maybe less uh here's
articles about engelbart we just had a
uh an open house online uh hosted by my
friend Carl henr uh about Doug Doug
engelbart's 99th birthday and a bunch of
people who knew a lot about um Doug and
who had met him and worked with him
showed up for this Zoom call and we had
a lovely lovely
time
awesome thank you thank you love of all
for the question okay another set of
topics please address the openness and
closeness of open Global mind and just
more generally like what about it is
open source what is transferable in and
out um what what um aspects of the
communications around the project and
the development um how has that changed
Through
Time thank you great thanks for asking
about open Global mind uh what we do is
pretty much always under U CC Z or you
know just just a tributus or cc0 or
something like that uh we're trying to
put open things in the world we haven't
created a lot of Open Source software
we've done some uh uh some messing
around we have a call on on Mondays
called free Jerry's brain where we uh
wrote some code and then put it over on
GitHub I don't know that anybody knows
it necessarily exists but but we use
things like GitHub in order to put
things out in the Commons uh our
conversations are open anybody can join
ping me or I think if you go to open
Global mind it says click here to join
the community and that'll put you on our
Google group mailing list we try to use
open source software where we can uh but
the brain is not open source and Google
Groups is not really open source so we
we have sort of limitations in that way
a bunch of the conversations we have
about are about how do we ideally go
into fully open infrastructure the way
Wikipedia runs on Wikimedia and the wik
media engine and is fully open source so
we've not written a as I said we've not
written a bunch of code but all the
contents uh when I when I showed you the
ogm zoom calls um all of this content is
uploaded to YouTube for everybody to use
and see and comment and reuse in any way
you want uh we do that intentionally
these are kind of slow conversations
about the the process and uh you can
you're welcome to join these
conversations any way you
want awesome thank you love evolve
another question how does this support
making better decisions together
H so
um let me just go to decisions for a
second back decisions market research no
I didn't want that
um better data for there we go making
better decisions together I've got under
oh which I had under open GL L and under
decision-making
um one of the pieces of tools for
thinking one of the subcategories is
things like um argumentation maps and
decision matrices and decision tools and
all those kinds of things so under
decision-making there should be power
tools for decision-making for example uh
there's there there are a bunch of
tools most of which nobody's ever heard
of very few of which people have used a
lot but some of which are really really
helpful and when we do for example
public discourse for decision- making in
communities or large scale elections or
things like that we're drowning in
information and advertisements for the
candidates and all that and we don't
really have a lot of collective data we
might use together and I think a big
piece of what we'd like to do and I
don't think ogm open Global mind is
going to achieve this on its own at all
but there are a lot of communities that
are neighbors of ours or friends of ours
uh Jamie Joyce with the society library
for example is doing really really great
work and is just coming out with some
interesting things right now
um here's Jamie and here's the society
Library
TSL uh she's also connected to canonical
date debate lab there's something called
the Great American debate uh which she's
also connected with there are a bunch of
efforts to figure this out which I'm
trying to figure out how do we point to
them how do we help improve them how do
we help link them to one
another and uh and then how do we
popularize them and make them more
accessible to everybody else which I
think is key that if we don't wind up
using some power tools we're going to
end up drowning in the information
torrent all the time anyway uh so the
general category I put this under I
guess is sensemaking and I know you've
done a bunch of work in sensemaking as
well I think that's one of the ties that
that binds us um I think Collective or
collaborative sense making is a huge and
important Horizon that we are neglecting
at our
Peril um instead what's happening
is one of one of my tropes one of the
things that came up in my head because
of my use of the brain was uh and also
my knowing too much about how how
intellectual property is overprotected
is the idea
that we are drowning in the information
flood because everybody invents all flow
tools and no stock tools and here I'm
borrowing
um stocks and the notion of stocks and
flows from System Dynamics and a lake is
a stock of water a river is a flow of
water and if you kind of look around at
the information environment you'll find
out that everything is flow and very
very few things are stock so Instagram
Snapchat Twitter blogging you know the
newsfeeds email SMS texts WhatsApp all
those things are all flow they're all
flow and one thing I ask people when I
have any kind of audience is hey when
something good goes by in the flow do
you have a place to put it where you
know you'll find it again and maybe it's
even improved somewhere and so as I'm
saying 26 years ago I happened across
this tool that mapped they they pitched
me this tool that mapped really nicely
to how my brain happens to work which
might be how 10% of the population's
brains work maybe it's 6% I have no idea
I'd be really interested in a study says
here are the major subgroupings of how
people think and here are the tools that
best fit how you represent things how
your workflow works all of that right um
and so there's so few things one of the
cool things about Wikipedia is that it's
a stock of information wikis are stock
but everything else is flow and so I
think that sensemaking requires us to
slow down and feed the stock of
information thoughtfully to curate with
care and then to compare notes and I'm
really interested in what Steve
Bannon who I'm not a big fan of but I've
got Steve Bannon in my brain and I went
and I I uh listened to
um where's the interview I'm looking for
oh under articles about
Bannon
uh hold on let me just go to ban
assertions because I know I've got that
so Steve Bannon interviewed by zany
Menon Betos oh this is Bannon after
Trump's Administration role I should
connect this up to Steve Bannon directly
done so I listened to this um interview
by the the editor-in chief of the
economist and here's what I heard Bannon
say now I've never met the man I haven't
talked with him but I'm really
interested in comparing notes actively
in some space like this so that we might
make better decisions together and Bon
wants to just as far as I can tell he
wants to accelerate the destruction of
today's institutions so that he can be
the guy to rebuild the new ones and he's
trying to work with you know a far right
people around the world to do that and
knowing that's interesting I have a
thought here Brannon is a brilliant evil
strategist there's a little purple by
the way usually means editorial on my
part and yellow usually means hey
there's a bunch of stuff here yellow
yellow is collections white is the
default color for all thoughts anyway so
I hope that answers a piece of the
question there's a lot to it okay let's
let's continue this is what happens when
you've been doing something semi
obsessively for 26 years but I could be
making diaramas of San Francisco's Bay
Area Waterfront out of used toothpicks
and there was a there is an artist who
did that um but it wouldn't be as useful
as this I
think well let's get to this question of
use in the chat still in all of this I'm
not hearing how Jerry's brain helps
people so
where here's a topick goldgate high
bridge guy stepen sorry that's beautiful
so how this how do people use it where
have you seen it be useful um in the
past 26 years and and what are you
excited about for its like embodied
pragmatic use cool so I own Jerry's
brain.com theb brain.com will take you
to the company that made the software I
did I had nothing to do with making the
software as I said I was on their first
press tour um I do own Jerry's brain.com
where you can go and you can launch my
brain and you can go browse around it
all you want uh the the URL
B.J all lowercase will also take you
directly to my brain on the web so if
you can write that down or remember it
and I get emails from people because the
brain is not a great collaboration tool
so somebody has to find me and send me
an email but I get a bunch of emails
from people um that say Hey thank you
for publishing your brain I've learned
how to use it and I noticed that you
don't have this have you thought of
adding it or whatever and if I don't
have it I'll add it if if I do have it
but it's just named something different
I'll write them back and I'll say
whatever I'm basically way more obscure
than I would like to be because the tool
is so quirky and sometimes frightening
to people and as I said if you if you
kind of get used to it um I I've
discovered that I did a kind of a a
survey just a a small survey of people
there's a out on the long tail there's a
bunch of people who are very happy going
to my brain without me and have figured
out how to use it and get around and
learnu and one of my friends more than a
decade ago said Jerry I've learned that
when I hit a new topic that I don't know
very much about one of the first things
I do is I go to your brain and see what
you found uh because often the things
that I found are are have don't have any
current Google juice so they won't show
up in a Google search but they're still
really useful documents right or videos
or whatever um and then there's another
piece of the tale which is people who
find the brain really useful but only
when I'm giving a tour or there to
answer questions and I totally
understand that it's just not very very
good leverage of my time but I love
doing that so I tried uh years ago I
tried as a piece of my business model I
put up the website pick Jerry's
brain.com and I put a a pricing schedule
up but I really didn't publicize it very
much um but I thought hey I would love
to make a living using both brains to
help people sort through problems
because I love troubleshooting things on
the Fly and you know and as you can see
I can I can use this thing on the Fly uh
pretty easily um and as I said earlier
but I didn't explain very well I really
want what I've built here to be an
inoculation into the big fungus and I
think the big fungus or whatever it
winds up being called because my history
is I'm pointing in the right direction
but I don't name the thing properly I
wrote an I wrote an an issue
of I wrote an issue of Esther's
newsletter in 1995 1996 titled What's a
Zen then it turns out web blogs show up
in '97 but I described web blogs in in
'95 right in June of 95 I described web
blogs but I called them Zen so I'm
trying to say that this big fungus I
think thing is going to exist and I'll
book Mark a question that we should
probably address which hasn't been asked
in your in your live chat yet which is
hey doesn't gen just obsolete all this
heavy lifting manual curation work thing
and I don't think so I I I think so I
have a thought
um
uh have the thought does chat gbt
obsolete note
taking right which has come up in a
couple of our recent calls that's how I
make the links here and I don't think I
think chat gbt supercharg is not taking
and I also think that things going
through our heads are really important
and us memorializing things in some
explicit way is also important I'm
incredibly interested in the
complimentary inter twil of my brain and
the new Cyber brains in gen I think
that's a really really wonderful
Frontier to explore but I don't think
that we should just turn into the people
on the couches and Wall-E and just rely
on the the big new AI to do all the work
for us I don't think that ends
well so many fun directions and
questions let's go back to free energy
principle and just kind of situate
oursel there of course there's many
research or theoretical things like we
could talk about how this is digital
stigmergy and about how we're in now a
feedback with our pherone distribution
and moving the Pebbles around um and
just the level of tangibility it
brings and um about the experience and
the craft of the learning and the work
and the
attention and about situating yourself
some people might have a more visual or
they do a Memory Palace other people
might really be on the Fly and super
Nimble with their Notes app and it's
kind of like whatever
works and all the learning that goes
into it and then this is one trajectory
this is like the Grand Canyon of tools
probably with a lot of lock in on up
left down lock in on software in and out
or limitations and all these different
things as any Canyon would be expected
to be after being worn down and that's
what transports the water and the flow
and is the stock so it's not exactly
just like a river but it's like amazing
to see that like yeah this is one
incremented
trajectory with no claims to be anything
other than one filament in the broader
mycelial Network and who else is in that
Network and how do we know and how do we
share how do we trust all these big
questions about our attention and our
information environments so it's just
awesome to see how far this has come and
then like what it
elicits
I love that and you're you're right on
it you're I what you're saying makes
complete sense to me and is is a lot of
why I'm doing this
exactly
um okay one one angle could be about uh
knowledge systems of and for cognitive
modeling another possible direction
would be um the collaborative sense
making and decision
making and
what where's where do you see this going
you mentioned generative AI like where
do you see some adjacencies or ways that
that are exciting right now yeah I think
that the the lwh hanging fruit may be
the collaborative decision-making and
just figuring out issue mapping or
whatever whatever else you want to call
it and as you've seen here it goes by
lots and lots of different names but how
and and and it's complicated it's really
complicated because sometimes we don't
even mean the same thing by the same
word
right if I ask you what is democracy or
what is
capitalism we're going to have a really
good long time even getting to a
consensus description uh never mind if
four other people join our conversation
so this is hard and it takes time but it
turns out that other people have have
sort of wrestled with a lot of these
issues and made really good sense of
them and if we find them and click their
answers into the puzzle there're sort of
like shortcuts right and instead of
philosophers and philosophies being
these far-off silos of thinking like oo
somebody's a heiger uh you know uh
scholar why don't we sort of glue these
things together to figure out what are
the piece parts that make a lot of sense
and then the huge question is how do we
present what makes sense how do we make
our way through it how do we pick our
way through the forest uh and there I
just have to say we have to try a lot of
different ways we have to try a lot of
different presentation methods um um
there's a whole bunch of different ways
in which people absorb what's happening
in the world and make their own sense of
it and then make an attempt to explain
their perspective on it to someone else
um and I wish we were doing a whole lot
more of this I wish we it's funny I did
a podcast with Tiago Forte
um I did a a podcast with Thiago uh and
someone else where we were talking about
uh his use of he's the build the second
brain guy and I learned in this podcast
that his second brain which is's famous
for is his private external brain and
his third brain is actually when he
publishes anything outside that's how he
thinks about it and I I I sort of did a
face palm because I realized that
everything I put in my brain is by
default public I have to open a thought
and click this little lock symbol to
make anything
private and when I click this little
lock symbol then a little lock shows up
under the icon and you don't see a lot
of locks here right there's one over
here here um so I'm actually outboard
most of the time and working as openly
as I can in an obscure little corner of
the world because of the obscurity of
the tool and the the scariness of the
tool but I'm I'm particularly interested
in how do we make the tools less scary
how do we encourage people to share a
lot more about what they think and see
um
and I had a a wish wear idea some time
ago be maybe before even El musk 8
Twitter and renamed it x uh of what if
Twitter had a service where it would
show you from its own analysis how many
of your retweets were basically known uh
known
misinformation that'd be a really
interesting service maybe a third party
could do this as well but just to see
that oops dang you know 10% of what I
retweeted or 80% of what I've been
retweeting is known misinformation and
it could sort of show you why and where
that would be really interesting for for
decision-making as well and and
then
[Music]
um I have a thought called emotion and
membership Trump reason most of the time
so everything I've been talking about so
far in this call is really about reason
and logic and evidence and sense making
but I will I will be among the first to
say that well hell most of what we make
decisions on is do I like this person or
does this fit my narrative or any of
those things and and will this will
agreeing with this get me kicked out of
my tribe that's huge that's just
absolutely huge and and so I'm
interested in that side of it as well I
think that if we don't address uh
emotional resonance and all of the very
subtle things um I was reading a book
about uh intergenerational trauma on my
flight home this morning um and
apparently um trauma has epigenetic
effects trauma affects gene expression
and you are not born with a clean slate
of whatever the hell DNA your parents
had you were born with some pre
conditions that have to do with things
that happen maybe even several
Generations back in your family if
especially if they weren't dealt with in
different ways and I'm like oh right I
know exactly where to look in my family
history for those things and I'm I'm
about to embark on that journey and and
so this is I guess I'm a scattershot an
everywhere all at once a little bit kind
of effort guy and that doesn't turn out
a lot of things that look monolithic and
and knowable right um although in my
neob books group I'm I'm busy writing in
markdown as nuggets a book about
designed from trust which is one of the
ideas that showed up in my quest over
the last uh couple
decades thank you for these awesome
points like as we're turning over I'm
getting the sense of like the uh the
nestmate ants walking on a pingpong ball
and sort of on a treadmill moving left
moving up and down forward and backwards
and and modifying but mainly just
Scavenging over and like another aspect
of the hope that automated or synthetic
intelligence systems will step in and do
this work it's like there's this amazing
openness like wow what else could you
have done with that time and then
there's like who you really are what you
really showed with skin in the game and
attention in the game and like there was
like the journey too so if the journey
is important and seems like it is then
there's this element of like revisiting
it yeah if you just wanted to have all
the wiki links you could just download a
snapshot of Wikipedia and never look at
it um and that's as good as not
happening attentionally or if you
Traverse just three wikipedia
pages and then you add another
connection
you're spinning the web and making a
colony can be daunting to start but also
very exciting and clean slate to start
and then the challenge is as these um
peculiarities or just customs of
different knowledge systems
interact a lot like different people's
interacting on the earth and now in the
informational space we have new ways of
these like knowledge systems the
semantics and the syntax all interacting
too and so you're you're looking ahead
to to this challenge
that's not ahead of us so much as it's
already happened and is
ongoing and uh it's really interesting
also what you said about it being not
monolithic and about how many custom
works and what looks monolithic versus
what is this more ristic or
dispersive knowledge
way that seems to also cooccur and
understand like the affective and the
personal and the community components of
knowledge and the people which are a
fundamental component in your work as
much as um the time and the the place
and the publication all
that I totally agree and you reminded me
of a couple things I have I just went to
ryom and Del and gatari book a thousand
plateus mil uh and then here's visions
that have inspired Builders of global
brains so d shardan
noosphere uh the MX uh from vanever Bush
I'm not sure exactly how to pronounce
his name uh indra's net which comes out
of uh
uh basically
Buddhism uh in lots of different places
these are all visions of um how
knowledge or wisdom or insights get
shared and built there've been a bunch
of them and they're really exciting and
nobody's really gone there in fact uh
the encyclopedia
Galactica uh uh from Asam Mouse
Foundation series is a version of this
right so if you've been watching the
foundation series on apple plus that's
what is's that's what uh Harry suman's
trying to build uh and then another
piece that you reminded of is if we
externalize more of what we believe it's
a kind of
vulnerability it's it's a kind of
putting yourself out there in a way that
like well this is what I think and and
and I will add that these days that
feels really more dangerous than it used
to because we see the kinds of doxing
and uh well I'm not doing this
anonymously but we see that the kinds of
backlash that there can be in particular
for very effective ideas sometimes if
there's a very effective critic uh
Michael E man just won a million dollars
in punitive damage for defamation
yesterday
um for uh basically idiots who were
trying to take him down as a very
effective climate uh uh climate change
evangelist right and um so here's uh
here's this I this I
added yesterday there it
is and that's really interesting and so
it's dangerous to put what you believe
out there especially gets popular and I
got to say that's a little fear in the
back of my head but I'm so obscure that
I'm not especially concerned about it
right now and then the other thing is
that if we can externalize what we
believe into a place where other people
can find it on their own
time it's a little way of doing one of
the most one of the most um useful
things you can do when you've hit
somebody who has a really different
opinion from yours instead of trying to
convince them of anything you can just
ask tell me more or and why do you
believe that
or what made you what made you come to
that conclusion something like that
and asking someone to put what they
think or even just to like what they
think out there in the world is is a
form of of doing that inquiry on your
own time and I think the more we can
find our way to each other um listening
with care it's a whole bunch of people
who feel like they're just not nobody's
listening to them
nobody um and and they've got a lot to
say they've thought about things long
and hard and they they haven't found an
outlet or a community or we're sort of
in an epidemic of not
[Music]
listening um which is a thought I've got
in my
[Music]
brain and and so in a sense what what
I'm trying to do here is weave all these
things together into a narrative that
might make sense for how we deal with
the important issues that all
[Music]
facing ah there's a ton there yes in
active inference where we're especially
interested in this setting of like two
Nest mates having a conversation through
interactions or through fairmon so two
Quantum
conversants talking through the
holographic boundary through the
information environment are the real
living Quantum agents and their
communication through through the
interface
and people are using interfaces for all
of what they read and who they know
unfortunately that data has been
enclosed by surveillance capitalism and
such and so it's already happening now
this is a different pherone profile this
is like a colony with a interior
decoration and architecture that's
culturally different but clearly
authentic and natural to the
inhabitants and uh it just opens up that
question
of where the information Niche and the
action Niche and the attention Niche are
that will respect and allow for
flourishing of all of the variation in
our situations and all the cognitive
diversity agreed who else is doing this
like I I've got my little collection of
communities trying to fix world problems
I know people like Gordon brander who's
doing the noosphere protocol and a bunch
of other people nibbling on pie of this
I've talked with Danny Hillis who built
a company that Google bought that is
Google's knowledge web and who had now
has another startup where he's trying to
figure out some piece of this like like
who where what who who wants to who
should I whose door should I knock
on there's so many ways to respond to
that it's a great question it's an
eternal question and it's a um and the
traces some of them could be
recorded and yet it reflects like this
living weaving tapestry so even when I
see all these companies but but many of
them of course are no longer and so
being able to share um index cards you
could have a different biology um
definition you can have a different
biography for Carl friston but let's
agree that Carl friston index card is
what it is first start um and then like
from there how do we coordinate on the
semantics and yes there is this um scene
within a scene of the second level
Knowledge
Management um which actually connects
back to Douglas engelbart and the ABC
concept and the improving Improvement
and so on
[Music]
MH it's interesting I didn't find that
much good stuff about uh ABC and such
but I put ABC under Triple Loop
learning uh which is you know learning
to learn and kind of improving the
system itself but here's ABC under Doug
uh here's a couple articles about it and
he also believed in network improve
networked Improvement communities which
came up by the way in the 99th birthday
conversation I just pointed to and this
is a really lovely idea and I think I
think of ogm maybe as one of those so
maybe I'm going to do this just for
fun and I'll just read a comment evolve
I think Jerry's familiarity with the
terrain and particularly his Narrative
of the trajectories is critically
valuable and again this is just the
limited traces even all the typing you
could do in the world wow great video
effects you you know more that this just
evokes and that's what I find very
interesting in also considering like
knowledge work as a craft is like the
difference between know how and know
that and implicit knowledge and knowing
where to look and I know where I put
that Pebble I know which document to
look in I know when to just really
quickly do contrl F really quickly when
to do right click like exactly knowing
how to work within a knowledge
environment which is something that
takes months to years to really build
just like anything knowing how in the
environment and co-creating the
environment can go above and beyond
knowing that anything because knowing
that
is what these Foundation models are so
excellent with right
now totally agree one of my other
leading edges right now is uh I believe
that our future is increasingly Cyborg
and Cyborg is the word I landed on I had
to try out a bunch of other words I
still really like cyborg but
increasingly we're going to meld with
technology in different ways the
runnerup word was centor but I don't
like it as much um but but how do you
how might we be good cyborgs is actually
a question that pops out of that and
there's two diff very different opposite
ways to interpret that question one is
good cyborg good cyborg like I've been
domesticated and I'm part of you know
part of the the Borg the other way of
thinking about that is how can we be
ethical participants in this
increasingly synthetic Blended hybrid
stigmergic
medium to make sense of and fix the
problems that are that are around us um
some of which are just alienation
loneliness and not listening others
which are scientific in nature and like
you know or economic in nature right
yeah like a common term or attractor and
active inference for describing the is
there like the scientific side is the
ecosystems of shared intelligence and
talking about these ecosystems of
arising cognitive functionality with all
different kinds of things that range
from very simple to sophisticated to
unknown and how active helps us model
those things however
even a total snapshot of the location of
every molecule awesome isn't going to
help us pick a direction to trim tab
when it comes to addressing these issues
that you raised and so that is where we
need something that goes beyond the
descriptive okay well here's a uh you
know carbon copy of the whole ecosystem
of share intelligence and yet it has so
many adjacent posses that go through the
bottleneck of our attention and action
that that we need a community context
and we need each other and development
and all these other
features that are
not just the cut and dry that the formal
system can
be totally agree you just brought two
things to mind one of which is I don't
think there's one answer to this I think
that the solutions need to be adapted
locally and will be a method of
development I really like is just
storytelling hey here's a bunch of
stories about what people in similar
situations to yours did um does any of
these smell good to you do you want to
try any of them so I have a thought
called I have a thought called
revitalizing cities for example which I
really like and under here I put a whole
bunch of here's community-led
development uh here's indigenous people
taking back control of their towns local
living economies uh the living machine
motor city mapping etc etc but most
people don't know a lot of these stories
if I heard some of these stories and
then said oh oh oh uh the edible
landscapes in Todd Moran England sound
really cool maybe we could do something
like that with our community then okay
great here's a little bit of a template
or a boilerplate or a project plan for
what they did go customize it make it
your own take out all of this do all of
that do whatever and only when that
happens I think when when the the people
in whatever the community is make the
choices appropriate the tools but they
need to hear a that there that there's
stories of Hope anyway out in the world
because a lot of people lack hope but B
that this is very doable right that the
barriers to trying some of these things
are really actually quite low they just
take initiative and doing things so so
there's a piece of of the approach I'm
trying to take which is very fractal and
distributed and uh bottom up from
wherever I don't think there's like one
there's not one Vision we all have to
agree to for this thing to work and then
the second thing I wanted to say is and
this is a different thought altogether
but one of the things I want to do with
these nuggets of wisdom is instrument
them as many as possible so that they're
more useful in the world and I'll give
you one example for this
um there's a there's a um a pattern
language called liberating structures
and it's a pattern language about
facilitation and one of the best known
patterns in it is called one two4 all or
also think pair share and all it says is
hey as a facilitator if you have a big
group with a complex issue you might
want to give them all time by themselves
one pair them up put them in fours and
come back to plenary one two four all
super simple most people don't know that
this exists it's really powerful what if
right now you and I are in Zoom what if
there was a little Zoom bot that was
helping facilitate helping you
facilitate or me if I was facilitating
that said hey Daniel might you want to
use one 12 for all right now You' be
like what's that here's what it is okay
good can I help you run it and this is
what I mean by instrument which is again
the wrong word probably but a piece of
code could then set up breakout rooms
name them put cues in the chat Usher
people in and out of breakout rooms um
basically do the choreography that a
facilitator has to do online and
obviously there's an analog in person um
but how do we take more and more nuggets
of wisdom and do that with
them so that and make it open source
code make the knowledge open source make
it available get the word out all that
kind of stuff but then all our
facilitators game goes up right if the
if the nuggets are any
good awesome two points so first that's
an example of the synchronous
facilitation augmentation and also the
async augmented facilitation like what
if one year after every single edit to a
document or to a brain or a shared
whatever it checks back in and ask you
to revisit just for fun or or um for
some fraction it asks for review from
other people and just connects to Dot
more async not just the the synchronous
um and then to make an active inference
point so you talked about like kind of
showing these inspiring or high agency
or sustainable or whatever positive
attribute as an examplar and what that
means and so very interestingly in
active inference actions are selected
based upon being the likeliest thing to
happen the path of least action not like
the most rewarding in a kind of reward
or reinforcement learning setting alone
and so there's a lot of world States or
Community states that seem like well
yeah it would be rewarding if everyone
in a 200 mile radius had stable housing
around me that sounds great I would feel
better and yet everyone can agree up and
down and left and right on that and yet
it can be understood as unlikely and
therefore is never a future that comes
to be and of course um delusions don't
lead to success believing that something
is a certain way and hitting the wall is
not going to lead to survival or
persistence but that's this kind of
tension with the expectations and
preferences and then hearing that
something is possible okay so then you
know a coin lands on the third side one
in a million
times but for the five times before or
after it did it was actually like one in
10 and on the time it did it was one out
of one so maybe it could be likely that
this is going to happen in this way for
our community even though it seems super
tough and totally like it's over but
then it was also over for them and then
they were
back I'd love to explore that a little
bit with you sometimes what we think is
possible or what the model thinks is
possible can change dramatically if you
shift the
[Music]
frame and and so sometimes I think we
make faulty assumptions about what the
what the realm of possibility actually
is we think that nothing could could
really change but it turns out that a
lot could change very quickly we just
haven't heard that story don't know that
idea don't know what the useful frame is
one of my heroes is a guy named Milton
Ericson who was a hypnotherapist back in
the Great Depression who had Polio a
couple times in his life suffered
chronic pain um and learned how to use
hypnosis to do therapy and he was known
for his handshake induction which would
which means when we do a handshake with
somebody we kind of go into a little
lyic Loop where kind of out of our
control and he would linger in the
handshake to the point where when he let
go of your hand you were in trance and
then he would address your unconscious
and give you new options and he was
known for having very short therapy
sessions that made massive changes in
the the client's life partly because he
was reframing what they thought was
possible what their unconscious
understood was the Repertory of behavior
whatever else that might be and that's
kind of a weird weird example maybe to
use here
but I'm a believer that if we can affect
how people see the world in one another
in some simple but profound ways that
that whole realm of Spectra of
possibilities can shift dramatically to
where things that seem impossible
suddenly you're like well duh of course
why don't we do
that right and and then a much simpler
example is ride
sharing and this goes to my design from
trust thesis which is before somebody
actually had like an app and was able to
step into a stranger car and go
someplace and get dropped off and make
the payment and feel relatively safe
some you know most people would have
said that's crazy why would that work
who's going to do it who would climb
into a car no way that's going to work
and then it did one of the symptoms of a
system designed from trust is that your
sphincter tightens a little bit you have
this feeling like whoa that's certainly
impossible Wikipedia is designed from
trust and I asked people do you remember
the first time you learned how Wikipedia
works was your reaction something like
God what idiot invented that of course
that can't
work and then you went in and explored a
couple things you knew something about
and you're like well hell it seems to be
working and how do I get more of this so
what you just said about about what's
possible what what you know what the
next most likely thing is the woo way
the the action through least action
which is a principle I
love I think is shapable a lot by how we
talk about describe perceive understand
and share the context and the frame of
possibilities for our situation and I'm
not sure that the machines will
understand
that thank you all great points in
active inference people talk about the
affordances it comes up in digital
design too but those are the capacities
for action
and there was a lot there so um for
anyone who's watching let's see any
remaining questions and then otherwise
as we kind of come close to this
chapter's end um like what can a young
person do what can an elder do how can
we all participate and feel around for
what we
want awesome questions I uh I think
overgeneralizing about Generations is
diff is is a little fraught but I I
don't mind the generations kind of stuff
until it gets overdone I look at the
youngest Generations right now and I
think that there's sort of a dumbbell
distribution in my mind over on one side
are a bunch of young people who are just
on the honic treadmill they're like the
world is screwed our elders are handing
us a pile of dung and we might as well
just get what we can and enjoy all this
clicking and scrolling and whatever ever
else and go for it out at the other end
of the dumbbell are some kids who are
way smarter than me who grew up with
with the power tools at their fingertips
and understand how they work who
understand social dynamics and people
and who are really trying hard to change
the world in ways that I find hugely
admirable and in the middle are a bunch
of other other kinds of sorts of people
but but I don't have some kind of gloomy
doomy feeling about young people oh like
like we've always said oh the young folk
these days I think the young folk these
days are in large measure phenomenal and
fantastic and I would love to be helpful
to them if if there's any way I can uh
please share my email in with the
podcast it's associate Gmail so a t
gmail.com I'm happy to connect you
please join my communities so that we
can talk about this and be of help to
you there's there there's too many older
white guys like me in my communities and
I want to be helpful to young people and
people who don't look like my
demographic
whatsoever um and I think a part of the
problem and and and I I see my mom died
a couple Decembers ago and she was the
last of my and my wife's sort of Elders
uh to pass so we have no no parents left
and I but I I had a lot of trouble with
her for the last five years of her life
and I care a lot about what Elders do
and how to deal with elders and all of
that and I think that Elders carry a lot
of the wisdom that we've been talking
about that that the many different kinds
of things that matter that
Solutions found to thorny issues uh
simple clever hacks to to social
situations or facilitation or whatever
else Elders carry that and then they die
with it and it goes away once they die
mostly so can we encourage them to tell
their stories to their families to share
their wisdom with us in some very simple
way and now that we have really good
text to you know speech to text
transcription and some chat you some
some llms and gen out there um can we
feed that into the mall and and make it
more visible more useful etc etc so I
think there's plenty of things to
do uh that aren't easy to get into quite
yet you you've got to scratch and work
to figure out how and where but if more
people ask for it and more people work
on it we might actually make some
progress there and there's an epidemic
of not listening I said earlier there's
also an epidemic of loneliness um
consumerism individualism modern societ
that cuts Generations apart has sliced
and diced up the extended family to the
point where it's really easy to feel
isolated and alone the pandemic didn't
help and uh we've got a lot of work to
[Music]
do yeah wow awesome all right let's ask
some quick questions from the live chat
so Susan asks explain what open Global
mind is and its affordances please you
can just Briefly summarize what is open
Global mind what does it enable one to
interact with it sure ogm is a community
of practice uh people who show up
normally on Zoom calls we've never had a
face-to-face meeting we're working on
the problems around um collaborative
sensemaking mostly that collaborative
sense making very broadly spoken and we
have a bunch of standing our affordances
are
basically four plus standing calls every
week uh all of which are visible online
you can kind of go in my brain or on the
web and find all these different
artifacts and then now and then we'll
drop a nugget of something interesting
out but we don't we don't have a lot of
uh outputs um in principle the neob
books project should be turning out some
neob books which is what we're working
on right now uh but there's not a lot of
other artifacts that we've created thank
you could you analogously summarize and
give any updates on free Jerry's brain
what is the project what is its current
status so the brain software that I've
been showing you that we're still
looking at is proprietary software uh
and and the the company is somehow
miraculously still alive 26 years after
its its launch which doesn't happen to a
lot of little software companies but
I've always wanted to be part of a
broader Network in an open collaborative
environment where the brain was one of
many different ways of interacting with
the data but the data was highly
connected and woven in this mycelial
fashion we've been talking about so free
brand an attempt to do that we have not
succeeded so I'm still using the brain
as you can see and um the calls wind up
being the geekiest of the calls that
I've been talking about uh of these
standing calls and we um occasionally
take a bite out of this uh I will also
add that the version of the brain I just
upgraded to the brain 14 and there's a
little icon up here that says AI uh this
version actually has a connection to
GPT but it's done in a ways that I
haven't really used very much yet so I'm
just beginning to explore how to connect
my brain to GPT but that's part of what
we've been doing in fre Jerry's brain is
hey the brain now has an API so does GPT
um how do we bridge this Gap and some of
you will have noticed that I don't have
a lot of Pros descriptions in my brain I
have a lot of links and nodes and
therefore any kind of gen is going to
have to infer a lot as it wanders
through my brain and that's the that's
the the bump we're on right now is like
okay how do we how do we access that and
how do we get past the inference
hurdle all right another comment and
question from the
chat Mojo writes I think the inactivist
epistemic community defines the concepts
we embody does Jerry have a perspective
on the redefining of our epistemic
community by meta recognizing the
abstract nature of intelligence and how
different we could shape ourselves from
how we've been shaped through generation
trauma SL existing perspectival
flows that question is several pay
grades above me um because I barely
understand it as you can see I don't
have much under epistemic communities
I've got Peter hos and epistemology um
but I don't have much about Peter and
his father Ernst or his wife Mimi uh etc
etc
but there's I would love to just
actually sit and talk with was it Mojo
who asked the question um I'd love to to
sit and talk for a while because I need
to learn more about this and the the
book I'm reading right now um is showing
me that so much of what we don't speak
about and don't fix is just floating
around with us uh and really urgently
needs to be dealt with um my wife and I
attended a workshop a couple weekends
ago just fresh in our minds where we did
one of the things the group did was a
family
constellation which is a way to deal
with intergenerational trauma super
powerful method didn't understand why it
worked but it worked really powerfully
and uh in fact the the woman
facilitating said this always works we
don't know why
um so here's family constellations work
the inventor is Bert helinger he's the
guy who did this and that's one path to
accessing the kinds of trauma and other
sorts of things we're talking
about uh the book I'm reading right now
is by Mark woen and it's titled it
didn't start with you how inherited
family trauma shapes who we are and how
to end the cycle P published in
wow awesome stuff it's all important
work we and and it's stuff we can do
it's just we don't know it all
right very true so in closing where do
you want to
go where can people join you've
mentioned but how would you like to kind
of close this piece thank
you I'm trying to figure out how to do
what I'm doing and also make a living
over the next decade or two so I'm I'm
kind of narrowing down on the different
pieces of what I do um anyone with good
advice please feel free to reach out and
tell me if you want to join these
activities as I said uh there are uh
there's the Google group for ogm which
you can find easily by going to the ogm
website uh and a couple other things and
I'm especially interested in how to tip
more people into wanting to share what
they know in fruitful
ways so if you have hypotheses hunches
if you have your own activities on that
front that you'd like to share in um LMK
as we say uh I think that might be a
good place to end because I want to in
whatever time I have left I want to go
further into this uh to see if we can
make it actually help
okay GG
BRB AFK soon AFK thank you
bye
that